Guide to the Alfred P. James Papers, 1946-1956 DAR.1956.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Alfred P. James Papers
1946-1956
ULS Archives & Special Collections
James, Alfred Procter
DAR.1956.01
2.92 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
Dr. Alfred P. James was a history professor at the University of Pittsburgh between 1918 and 1956, researching eighteenth and nineteenth century Virginia and Pennsylvania. This collection contains correspondence and research notes created by James for his book, The Ohio Company: its Inner History, published in 1959.
Biography
Dr. Alfred P. James was a history professor at the University of Pittsburgh between 1918 and 1956. He taught briefly at the University of Arkansas and Ohio Wesleyan University previous to his appointment in Pittsburgh. James, a Rhodes Scholar, earned bachelor's degrees from Randolph-Macon College and Oxford University; master's degrees from Oxford and the University of Chicago; and a Ph. D. from the University of Chicago. His primary interest was eighteenth and nineteenth century Virginia and Pennsylvania. James published over thirty articles and was the author of The Writings of General Johns Forbes, The Ohio Company: its Inner History, George Mercer of the Ohio Company: a study in frustration, The Renaissance: an Outline, and co-authored Drums in the Forest, a history of early Pittsburgh.
After retiring from the university, James served as a trustee of the Historical Society of Western Pennsylvania. There he indexed the Society's journal, The Western Pennsylvanian Historical Magazine, which he had edited from 1922 to 1927. James was a member of the American Historical Association, Phi Alpha Theta, and was a charter member of the Phi Beta Kappa Society at the University of Pittsburgh. James died on November 17, 1971.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection is comprised of the research notes and correspondence of Alfred P. James relating to his book Ohio Company, its Inner History. The correspondence series documents James' communication with archivists and manuscript curators from institutions in the United States while in search of Ohio Company records. The transcriptions and research notes are typed copies of Ohio Company records dating between 1741 and 1823. These transcriptions have annotations and other notes created by James for his research.
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence, 1946-1956
Series II: Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1946-1949
Acquisition Information
Gift to the Darlington Memorial Library from Alfred P. James in January 1957.
Custodial History
These papers were created and owned by Alfred P. James during the mid twentieth century until he gifted them to the Darlington Memorial Library on January 17, 1956.
This collection was located in the Darlington Memorial Library in the University's Cathedral of Learning until 2007 when it was moved to the ULS Archives Service Center for processing, storage, preservation and service. However, it remains in the custodianship of the ULS Special Collections Department.
Previous Citation
Alfred P. James Papers, 1946-1956, DAR.1956.01, Darlington Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Ohio Company Papers, 1736-1813, DAR.1925.02, Darlington Collection, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Pittsburgh Waste Book and Fort Pitt Trading Post Papers, 1757-1765, DAR.1925.03, Darlington Collection, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Bibliography
"James, Alfred Proctor," Personal File, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh.
Transcripts; Copybooks; Archivists; United States -- History -- 18th century; Land grants -- Ohio; Public lands -- Ohio; Pennsylvania, Western; Ohio; West Virginia; Librarians; Maryland, Western; Loggstown (Pa.) -- History; Ohio River Valley -- History -- Sources; Correspondence; James, Alfred Procter; Ohio Company (1747-1779); University of Pittsburgh -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1946-1956; I.
  - Correspondence, 1946-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1946-1949; II.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains copies and typed transcriptions of Ohio Company documents dating from 1743 to 1823. The transcripts contain research notes and findings by Dr. James dating from 1946 to 1949.
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1743-1751 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1743-1751 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1751-1753 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1751-1753 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1753-1755 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1753-1755 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1755-1767 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1755-1767 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1768-1783 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1768-1783 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1784-1821 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1784-1821 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1744-1751 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1744-1751 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1751-1753 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1751-1753 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1754-1755 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1754-1755 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1755-1767 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1768-1783 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1785-1821 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1745-1821 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1744-1764 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1744-1764 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1743-1823 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1743-1823 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1752-1767 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1749-1752 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1752-1823 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1752-1823 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1752-1823 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - George Mercer Papers, 1763-1776 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1748-1768 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1748-1768 (Box 7, Volume 1)
  - Transcriptions and Research Notes, 1748-1768 (Box 7, Volume 2)